[Music]
Jordan Peterson has become hugely
successful what do you make of the
phenomena why do you think he's become
so successful now there is a drought of
authenticity and courage and Peterson
has found that hunger and he's tapped
into it and I I admire his ability to
detect it and to speak to it plainly in
a way that it resonates with I did we
were on a panel together in Vancouver
and I watched his talk and he described
his own surprise at how effective his
message had been and he basically said
that if he had outlined his message as
the core of a business model that it
would have looked laughable to him and
that he was as shocked as anybody that
people are resonating with it but when
when you live in a world that is as full
of crap as the world we live in where
people are advertising bullshit to you
from the moment you get up to the moment
you go to sleep and then somebody
finally tells you some truth that you
need to hear it's a relief it's a relief
just to know that there's some channel
that isn't compromised by nonsense and
he I don't think he's the only one
speaking truthfully but I think he is
speaking from the heart
and people know it he doesn't someone
who from his lectures takes evolution
seriously how does that overlap with
your work and how does it map onto your
work well I would say Peterson is an
exceptional psychologist in the sense
that at the moment academic psychology
is in a crisis where all of the results
that people have treated is true because
they had a statistical significance are
turning out to be difficult to replicate
and therefore probably fiction
Peterson is not swept into that madness
because he's chosen to stay in that
quadrant in psychology where there's
solid ground so he is I don't want to
say totally unique but somewhat unique
in that landscape as can you explain
what that means that he's chosen to stay
installed at Graham woods this is the
psychometrics you mean yes Peterson has
stuck with psychometrics where results
are replicated and the the model is
sound and so anyway he's less affected
maybe unaffected by the replication
crisis he is a psychologist takes
evolution seriously as all psychologists
should he can't be a specialist in
evolutionary biology so he's in some
danger of dabbling and not seeing the
full richness of some of the stuff that
he's interested in but nonetheless it is
to his credit that he takes it seriously
where most of psychology dispenses with
evolution entirely I'm an evolutionary
biologist you take psychology seriously
because I'm interested in human beings
and so a lot of the things I'm
interested in play out in Psychological
terms I'm not a specialist in psychology
but I have to grapple with it in order
to to understand the things I'm
interested in and so in some ways
there's a comparison we are either side
of a divide about which our home ground
is and which other discipline we are
engaged with because his his map is
really based on Jungian psychology the
idea of the shadow the idea of
integration of the shadow the idea of
the reality of myth and the usefulness
of myth and religion is that something
that maps onto your evolutionary biology
territory so I've been playing with the
idea of myth for a long time and my
conclusion has been that things that are
costly to us but that last must be
paying their way in some evolutionarily
positive fashion so myth clearly passes
this test
and when I heard Peterson talking about
it my thought was that we were aligned
as I listened more to him I realized
that there is an alignment to an extent
we both believe that those stories that
have persisted over time have a deep
value but then there's also a disconnect
where he imagines that these stories are
inherently timeless and I'm aware of how
many things that are long-lasting are
now not functional in the modern
circumstances because of the level of
evolutionary novelty so I hope to have
that conversation with him at some point
so in the Jungian psychology he talks
about the shadow he talks about kind of
the Jungian idea the roots of the shadow
reach all the way down to hell like
they're sort of I guess desire to to
dominate like does that map on to your
your model in some way I would say
Jungian psychology is a useful myth and
I you know I I don't mean that to sound
forger ative I think it's not true in a
narrow literal sense but many unions
have made progress because there's
something to it what I see is that we
are a very odd species we like every
species have a mission that's pretty
uninteresting that mission is to pass on
our genetic Spelling's to the exclusion
of alternative genetic Spelling's to the
extent possible we also have the most
amazing toolkit in nature for doing that
a toolkit that is capable of having
conscious thoughts and whatsmore
exchanging those conscious thoughts
between individuals we can set our
values we can say what would we like to
accomplish and what we would like to
accomplish is capable of being something
other than gene spreading so my feeling
is once you recognize how dangerous and
mind-numbing our evolutionary purpose is
you can't help but rebel against it and
if you rebel against it then you have
this marvelous machine that you can set
to a more interesting more noble more
meaning
full purpose and why wouldn't you who
wants to be an agent for a mindless
program for spreading particular
spellings to the exclusion of others
that's not an interesting game at all so
my sense is we face one of the greatest
puzzles that has ever been maybe it is
the greatest puzzle that has ever been
which is can we re author or purpose now
that we know how generic and dangerous
our evolutionary purpose is can we take
the machinery that was built for that
purpose the marvelous machinery set to
that terrible purpose can we repurpose
it to something worthy of us it seems a
lot of the reactivity of the mainstream
media and it was certainly the topic of
the Kathy Newman interview was around
gender and why do you think that is and
why as a evolutionary biologist someone
who sort of studies studies sex and
gender in detail why why do you think
that this has become the the crux of so
many of these conversations well I I see
it as a like a slow-motion train wreck
completely unnecessary
but can't be stopped because everybody
has a sense that they have a dog in this
fight and we all do but people do not
understand where their interests lie in
this discussion and so they are lashing
out for lack of a better term in an
attempt to shut down that which they
think threatens them but their map of
what is threatening to them and what
actually serves their interests is
almost random compared to the reality of
breeding systems and what people
actually want and the irony is inside of
evolutionary biology this is all pretty
well understood it's not like that is
getting male-female sexual dynamics what
they mean and what different social
systems are about so this conversation
there's no debate inside of evolutionary
biology about whether males and females
are basically the same
we all know that males and females are
not basically the same there are many
things about us that are the same but
there are so many things that are
different and those things that are
different may be inherited genetically
they may be inherited culturally but
they all have meanings it's not an open
landscape in which you can just design
whatever you want so what I see is
wishful thinking everywhere and people
imagining they are much more informed
about sexual dynamics than they actually
are I guess what a lot of people fear
when they hear evolutionary biologists
talk about sex roles is that where
they're trying to sort of reimpose roles
that were cast off in the 1960's and
1970's so this this is an important
misunderstanding the roles that we have
recently abandoned are almost
unbelievably ancient my favorite example
involves looking at a flower that
contains both male and female parts in
the same structure a flower that has
both male and female parts has a
difference of opinion within itself
about how enthusiastic to be about sex
with strangers the male parts are
gung-ho for it the female parts not so
much female parts in fact at a
structural level are coy they put the
pollen grains through a test in which
pollen tubes grow down through a long
structure in order to reach the OVA so
we can decide that we either do want to
retain female coyness in some form or
that we want to reject it but what we
can't do is decide that that was imposed
by some sort of Puritan viewpoint
amongst males and you know in recent
times it's not it it stretches back far
enough into the past that we can find it
across the animal kingdom and if we look
into plants that separately evolved but
nonetheless the same pattern emerges
there so we should alter the dynamics of
sexuality
or modern times and we should do so with
fairness in mind I'm very much in favor
of this I'm married to a woman who used
the world in masculine terms I mean she
lives in a way that makes sense in
masculine terms she goes to the Amazon
she you know enjoys adventure of a
certain kind I'm all in favor of women
doing things that are not traditionally
female but are not in favor of
pretending that femininity was invented
by men to keep women chaste or something
like that it wasn't invented by humans
at all
because this I guess is another part of
the discussion because from a sort of
postmodern viewpoint even using the
words masculine and feminine but they
assume that those are culturally defined
and then you get into a question well
what do you mean by masculine what do
you mean by feminine and you you then
sort of enter a language game and a loop
where they sort of don't refer to
anything but what you're saying is they
actually do refer to things you can
study right down to to flowers and to
plants and to things that are not that
are not human there's a actually a very
simple story that accompanies this truth
which is there are very few creatures in
which gametes are the same size there's
an unstable equilibrium in which gametes
are equal size and what that means is
that gametes in any creature that has
two sexes will tend to have one sex with
small mobile gametes and another sex
with large sessile Gamble's once you
have that dynamic you have an asymmetry
in the interest of the parents in
investing in those gametes small mobile
gametes are not worth investing heavily
and and large society mutes are worth
being choosy over because the investment
that they contain is greater now that
has almost nothing to do with us at a
direct level but every time we have had
creatures evolved in which there's an
asymmetry of investment in offspring you
get other things evolving as a
consequence like choose eNOS it is
natural that a creature that has larger
gametes should be choosy it is natural
that a creature that gets pregnant
should be choosy it is natural
that a creature that has offspring with
a long childhood should be choosey now
in human beings we have a really
interesting situation where men
reproduced by two strategies men can
love them and leave them in which case
they're not very choosy because why
should they be at an evolutionary level
and men more generally invest in their
offspring in which case they have every
reason to be as choosy as women do so
human beings are not some standard case
from nature they're a special case and
an interesting one but to imagine that
females being more reluctant about sex
was the idea of men who wanted to impose
something on women is preposterous it
exists in birds
it exists in insects it exists in trees
and when you're talking about sort of
masculine and feminine going down so
deep what I what I hear is sort of the
potential for that even to map on to
some of the ancient wisdom traditions
the idea of the the DAO as being in the
yin-yang going sort of right down into
being that you have this sort of
masculine and feminine dynamic playing
out you think that does that kind of
analogy work absolutely and in fact
there's an important evolutionary
principle discovered by a biologist
named Fisher Fisher's sex ratio
principle says that it is actually
although males can produce many more
offspring in a lifetime than females can
on average males and females produce the
same number because for every male that
produces an above average number of
offspring there's some male who produces
a below average number of offspring so
the variance in males is high the
variance in male in females is lower but
the average is equally valuable so sex
ratios tend to be even at birth because
there's no evolutionary advantage to
producing males or females in fact what
you want to do is produce that which is
in lower supply this is a perfect
yin-yang they are not symmetrical and
identical in that sense but they are
compatible symmetries that reflect
a balance between two forces and the
punchline to the joke is that we are not
one or the other
evolutionarily speaking all your genes
but a handful spend half their time in
female form at half the time in male
form and so they aren't really about one
of these two strategies winning out over
the other because half the time they
would be on the losing end it seems that
there's a confusion between is a nought
that a lot of the time you saw this in
the Jordan Peterson Kathy Newman
interview but Jordan Peterson was
describing the way that things are Kathy
Newman is immediately taking it as that
he was saying this is the way the things
should be you're you're saying that I
should I should do this is this is this
part of the the substructure of this
conversation the is art question is
absolutely basic you can't really have
any of the important topical
conversations that we need to have
without covering this ground and
realizing that to describe what is is
not to imply anything about what ought
to be or even what can be and maybe
that's the third partner in that in that
triad when we look at evolution and
biology we are looking at a completely
amoral landscape there are many
wonderful things in there there are
horrifying things in there evolution is
responsible for all of our best
characteristics and our worst so at some
level we should be having the
conversation not about well you think
this is what is there for you're
defending it as what ought we should be
having the conversation about what that
is do we want to retain what that is do
we want to jettison and how much freedom
do we have to move things and we have
much more freedom than than those who
are pushing a naive symmetry would
imagine we have a lot of freedom to
refigure the dynamics of male and female
and we should do it because this I guess
is the is the concern that when people
talk about evolutionary biology are
saying well this is our evolutionary
toolkit many women have different
evolutionary toolkits what people then
hear is
a sense of this is unchangeable this is
we're then in a binary between the
Conservatives view that we're kind of
basically we're going to have to go back
to the 1950s and the liberal idea and
how do we transcend that kind of that
the the culture war unfortunately there
is a kind of failure of understanding
that extends into evolutionary biology
and also exists in a widespread form in
public which has to do with evolution
being synonymous with genes so when
people talk they will say is it
biological or is it cultural well that's
not a good dichotomy it happens that
culture is equally biological as genes
and once we understand that then we will
realize that to say that some dynamic is
evolved and that's why it exists in the
present does not mean it's inflexible
because if it's evolved but it is
transmitted culturally we actually have
an opportunity to to alter that
landscape so if we look at for example
female fighter pilots there's no reason
that females should not be fighter
pilots if that's what they want to do
but warfare has always been the province
of men does it need to remain the
province of men that's a discussion we
can have but there's no technical reason
and obviously the fact that there are
female fighter pilots tells us that we
can retune that dynamic any way that we
think is right and lots of things in in
this in this area worked that way where
they are evolved there's a history but
it is transmitted in a way that it is
amenable to being altered I've often had
a sense that basically what's needed is
for the liberal worldview to be read
pilled in some degree that to accept
biology but then understand that it is
in some degree malleable rather than
being in sort of this reactivity to it
and this seems to be where we're getting
stuck at the moment I agree with you and
you know I've I've known for a long time
as I studied evolution as a progressive
that the left has an uneasy relationship
with evolution on the one hand it is the
defender of Darwin against creationism
traditionally on the other hand when it
gets to talking about evolution and
human beings the left is extremely timid
about what it may find and I think in
some sense it is afraid of a boogeyman
that just simply doesn't exist
evolutionary biologists as a rule tend
to be quite left-wing Dawkins in The
Selfish Gene starts out he says if you
you you should read this book as a
warning right about how we ought to
regard that landscape and the fact that
we must alter things in order that it
does not dominate our our view of the
world and I think the trick is going to
be to get people to listen long enough
so that they understand that the
conversation is not a power grab
nobody's trying to take anything from
them we're trying to alert people to
what that landscape looks like what
dangers it creates and what alternatives
we may have if we wish to pursue them so
I like I like your argument that the
left needs a red pilling I don't mean a
right-wing red pilling I mean a an
epiphany about what relationship it
should have with with evolution it seems
that there could be a resolution of
saying well certain things are fixed
certain things are real and so on the
other side he's pretty much got liberals
often arguing against reality or just
not facing reality but there seems to be
that there is the possibility of a
deeper resolution of this conversation
oh absolutely
both sides have a major blind spot and
were we to have one conversation where
we two have voices in it that understood
the underlying dynamics there is a
resolution that I think you don't win
everything but everybody wins a large
fraction of what it is that they
actually want there's a great deal that
is true about our evolutionary nature
and there's a tremendous amount of
freedom to change even many of those
things that were handed to us
evolutionarily so I'm waiting for that
conversation to happen and we have to
reduce the suspicion of each other and
the polarization in order to have that
it's got
you